Welcome back to Google Colab.
구글 콜랍에 잘 오셨어요
Here we are ready to explore the wonderful world of Tokenizers.
이제 토큰이들의 세계를 탐험해 볼까요?
So, uh, the first thing I'm going to do is do some imports.
먼저 할 일은 수입품 처리를 하는 거예요
And after I've done that, I want to mention this statement here.
그걸 한 후 여기 이 문장을 언급하고 싶어요
I forgot to mention this in the last video, but I have added it into that colab, so hopefully you
지난 강의에서 언급하는 걸 잊었는데 Colab에 추가했어요 어쨌든
found it anyway and read my explanation.
찾아서 제 설명을 읽어보세요
Uh, you may need to log in to Huggingface in Colab if you've never done that before.
콜랍의 포옹 사이트에 로그인해야 할 거예요
And this is the code that you use to do that.
그걸 위해 사용하는 코드가 이거죠
First of all, if you haven't already created your account with hugging face, you need an account with
먼저, 포옹하는 얼굴 계정을 아직 만들지 않으셨다면 포옹하는 얼굴 계정이 필요해요
It's free.
공짜예요
It's it's terrific and you will never regret it.
정말 멋지고 절대 후회하지 않을 거예요
So sign up at huggingface and then navigate to settings and create a new API token.
안기페이스에 등록한 다음 설정으로 이동해 새 API 토큰을 생성하세요
Giving yourself write permission.
스스로 허락하는 거죠
We won't need to use the right permission today, but we will in the future, so might as well set it
오늘은 올바른 권한이 필요 없지만 나중엔 필요할 테니 지금 설정하는
up right now.
게 좋아요
Then when you come back, you go to this key section here in the Colab and you add in a new secret.
다시 돌아와서 Colab의 이 키 섹션으로 가서 새 비밀을 추가하세요
The secret should say HF underscore token and the value should be your token.
비밀은 HF_token이라고 하고 값은 여러분의 토큰이어야 해요
And then all you have to do is run this code that will get the HF token from your secrets, and it will
이제 코드를 실행해서 기밀에서 HF 토큰을 가져오면 로그인 메서드를 호출할
then call this login method, which I imported here.
거예요 여기 불러왔죠
And that login method logs in to hugging face.
로그인 방법은 얼굴을 안는 거예요
Let's run that right away.
바로 실행하죠
And it's done.
다 됐어요
And you see it says I have rights permission right there.
여기 보면 권한이 있다고 나와 있죠
Okay, let's talk Tokenizers we are going to start with the fantastic llama 3.1, the iconic model from
토큰라이저에 대해 얘기해 보죠 환상적인 라마 3부터 시작할게요 1번, 메타의 상징적인 모델 오픈
meta, which paved the way for open source models.
소스 모델의 길을 닦았죠
Now, when you're using llama 3.1, meta does need you first to sign their terms of service.
llama 3을 사용하면요 1. 메타 서비스 약관에 먼저 서명하세요
And the way you do that is you visit their model page on Hugging Face, which is linked here.
모델 페이지에 방문해서 얼굴 안기기를 하면 돼요 여기 링크가 있죠
And at the top of that page, there are very simple instructions for what you need to do to sign.
그 페이지 상단에 서명하기 위해 해야 할 간단한 지침이 있어요
Uh, you should you'll need to supply your email address, and it's best if the email address that you
이메일 주소를 제공해야 하는데 포옹하는 얼굴 계정과 일치하는
supply matches your hugging face account.
이메일 주소가 좋아요
That means they get things done quickly.
I'm get it's get it. 일이 빨리 끝난다는 뜻이죠
In fact, they should approve you in a matter of minutes.
몇 분 내로 승인될 거예요
I've done this many times, including once late on a Saturday night.
토요일 밤늦게까지 여러 번 해 봤어요
I got approved very, very quickly.
아주 빨리 승인을 받았어요
I don't know whether that's just because they're really on the ball or whether it's all automated,
정말 꼼꼼해서 그런 건지 자동화되어 있어서 그런 건진 모르겠지만
but it's very quick indeed.
정말 빠르네요
And in case you think there's something evil with this signing terms of service, it's really if you
이 서비스 서명 약관에 뭔가 해로운 게 있다고 생각하실까 봐 말씀드리는데 작은 글씨를 읽어 보시면
read the fine print, it's about making sure that you're not going to use lemma 3.1 for anything nefarious
lemma 3을 사용하지 않도록 확실히 하는 거예요 1번, 비도덕적인 행동과 선한 의도가
and that you have good intentions, which is very much the case in this class.
있을 경우입니다 이 수업에서는 그런 경우가 많죠
So it should be no problems whatsoever signing that.
그러니 서명하는 건 문제가 안 될 거예요
Once you've done so, you will have access to all the variants of llama 3.1.
그렇게 하면 라마다 3의 모든 변수를 볼 수 있죠 1번요
It's one one sign and then it applies to the whole family.
하나의 간판이 가족 전체에 적용돼요
If you wanted to use one of the older llama three models, like llama 3 or 2, you would need to go
라마 3이나 2 같은 구형 라마 모델을 사용하려면 모델
and sign the terms for that family of models.
가족에 가서 계약서에 서명해야 해요
If for some reason you don't want to, or you're finding that they're not approving you right away,
혹시 하기 싫거나 당장 승인해 주지 않는 것 같으면
you can just skip to later when we start.
나중에 시작해도 돼요
Or you can just watch me executing for 3.1, and then you can pick up when we start working with some
아니면 제가 3번 실행하는 걸 보셔도 돼요 1, 다른 토큰라이저와 작업하기 시작하면
of the other tokenizers.
그걸 선택하세요
But with that, creating a tokenizer is this single line here.
하지만 이걸로 토큰라이저를 만드는 건 여기 이 한 줄이죠
Hugging face has this class auto tokenizer, which will create whatever subclass of tokenizer is needed
안는 얼굴에는 오토 토큰마이저 클래스가 있습니다 이 모델을 위해 필요한 토큰마이저의 서브클래스를
for this particular model.
생성하죠
Don't need to worry too much about that.
그건 너무 걱정하지 마세요
Just know that auto tokenizer is the one to do and you call the class method from pre-trained, which
오토 토큰마이저를 이용하면 됩니다 미리 훈련된 것을 이용해 수업 메서드를 호출합니다 즉, 미리 훈련된 모델이
means I've got a pre-trained model and I want you to create the tokenizer that's for that.
있다면 토큰마이저를 이용하여 이를 위해 개발하면 된다는 거죠
And that is the name.
그게 이름이에요
This is the model that we're using.
이게 우리가 사용하는 모델이에요
That's which you can take directly from the Hugging face hub.
안아주기 얼굴 허브에서 바로 가져올 수 있는 거죠
It's meta llama's meta llama 3.18 billion.
메타 라마 3이에요 180억 달러요
This trust remote code equals true when as as you bring in this tokenizer, it's possible for there
이 트러스트 원격 코드는 true입니다 토큰라이저를 가져오면 모델의
to be code that is part of of a model.
일부인 코드가 있을 수 있어요
And we're saying we know who meta is.
메타가 누군지 안다고 했잖아요
We know that this is fine so you can trust it.
이건 괜찮으니까 믿어도 돼요
If you don't include that, it will still work fine.
그것만 빼면 괜찮을 거예요
It just gives you a warning, an ugly warning.
그저 추악한 경고만 남겨요
So if you don't want the ugly warning, then just, uh, put that in there.
어글리 경고가 싫으면 그냥 Put을 해요
Okay.
네
With that, the next thing I'm doing is I'm using the text.
이것과 함께 다음으로 할 일은 텍스트를 이용하는 거예요
I'm excited to show Tokenizers in action to my LLM engineers, and we take that text as a string and
LLM 엔지니어들에게 토큰라이저의 작동을 보여드릴 수 있어 기쁩니다 텍스트를 문자열로 만들어 Tokenizer.incode로
we call tokenizer dot encode that text.
호출하죠
And then we will print the tokens that result.
그 결과의 토큰을 인쇄하죠
Here they are.
여기 있네요
It's something that's super simple.
아주 간단한 거예요
It's just a list of numbers.
그냥 번호표예요
Nothing more than that.
그 이상은 아니에요
Nothing magical about tokens.
증표는 마법과 아무 상관 없어요
They are just numbers.
그냥 숫자일 뿐이에요
And these numbers represent that text.
이 숫자들이 그 텍스트를 나타내죠
Let's see how many of them there are.
몇 개나 있는지 보죠
Well, let's start by saying how many, um, uh, letters were in that text that we gave it.
우리가 준 문자에 편지가 몇 통이나 있었는지부터 말해보죠
There are 61 letters in that text.
글자가 61개나 돼요
So now we can count the number of tokens.
이제 패의 수를 세면 돼요
And do you remember the rule of thumb for roughly speaking, the how many characters map to a token.
대략적으로 토큰 하나에 몇 글자가 매개되는지 기억하시나요?
On average, it's four on average.
평균 4개예요
Roughly.
대강요
Rule of thumb about four letters should be one token for normal English or if you have a lot of English.
경험상 네 글자는 토큰이 되어야 해요 영어를 많이 안다면 말이죠
So we're expecting for 61 letters.
61통의 글자가 예상되네요
We're expecting around 15 tokens.
15토큰 정도 예상해요
Let's see what we get.
get get을 해 보죠
15 tokens.
15토큰요
There we go.
됐어요
Exactly 15 tokens for this text.
토큰이 정확히 15개예요
Um, and we can in fact do this decode to turn our tokens back into text again.
이 디코딩을 통해 토큰을 다시 텍스트로 바꿀 수 있어요
So we're expecting to recreate the original text.
그래서 원문을 재창조할 거예요
And what we get is something similar, slightly different.
Get it은 비슷하면서도 약간 달라요
As you will see what we get back is the text that we were expecting.
보다시피 get get은 우리가 기대하는 텍스트예요
But at the front of it is something new, this this funny thing here, this set of text that says in
그런데 그 앞에 새로운 게 있어요 여기 재미있는 거요 비스듬한 대괄호로 기호 시작보다보다보다보다보다보다보다보다보다보다보다보다가
angled brackets are less than and greater than sign begin of text.
텍스트 집합이죠
What is this?
이게 뭐죠?
So this is something called a special token or all of the, all of what I've highlighted just maps to
이건 특별한 토큰이란 건데요 제가 강조 표시한 모든 게 하나의 토큰에 매핑된
one token.
거죠
In fact, this token here, this 128,000 token, um, and it is a special token which is indicating
사실 여기 이 128,000 토큰은 특별한 토큰으로 우리 모델에
to our model that it is the start of a, uh, of a text of a prompt.
프롬프트의 텍스트의 시작을 알려주고 있어요
Um, and so it's used for that purpose to be a special indicator to the LM.
그 목적으로 LM의 특별한 지표가 된 거죠
Now, again, you might be thinking, uh, okay.
이렇게 생각하실지도 몰라요
So does that mean that somehow the architecture of the transformer has to be set, set up so that it
그렇다면 변압기의 구조가 그런 종류의 토큰을 기대하도록 설정되어야
expects that kind of token?
한다는 뜻인가요?
Uh, and uh, as you're probably, uh, very comfortable now, the answer is no.
지금은 아주 편하실지 모르겠지만 제 대답은 안 된다는 거예요
That's not what it means.
그런 뜻이 아니에요
Uh, what this means is that in all of the training examples that it saw during training time, it was
이 말은 훈련 중에 본 모든 훈련 사례가 이런 식으로 설정됐다는
set up this way.
뜻이에요
The training examples began with this special token begin of text.
훈련 예시는 이 특별한 토큰에서 시작됐죠
So it's got used to through training expecting that.
훈련을 통해 그런 걸 기대하며 익숙해졌죠
And in order to ensure the highest quality output, one should recreate that same approach.
최상의 결과를 내기 위해서는 같은 방법을 써야 하죠
Uh, when feeding in new prompts at inference time.
새로운 먹이를 줄 때 추론할 때 나타나요
So hope that made sense.
이해가 되셨길 바라요
There's another method batch decode.
다른 방법으로 해독할 수도 있어요
And if you run that with your tokens what you get back instead of one string, you get back these,
그걸 토큰과 함께 실행하면 하나의 문자열 대신 이런 문자열
uh, little, um, sets of strings where each string represents one token.
집합을 얻게 됩니다 각각의 문자열이 토큰을 나타내는 거죠
So as I say, this first token here turned into this here.
말씀드렸듯이 이 첫 번째 토큰이 이렇게 변했어요
And then you can follow through to, to to see how that's working.
그러면 그게 어떻게 작동하는지 볼 수 있죠
Um, and there's a few things to note from this.
몇 가지 주의할 점이 있어요
Uh, as you'll see straight away, one of them is that in most cases a word mapped to a token, because
바로 보실 수 있듯이, 그중 하나는 대부분의 경우 워드를 토큰에 매핑한 것입니다. 왜냐하면 여기에는 아주
we've got very simple words here.
간단한 단어들이 있으니까요.
So excited, even though it's way more than four characters mapped to one token, because it's such
정말 신나요, 토큰 하나에 4자 이상으로 매핑되긴 하지만요 흔한 단어니까요
a common word, it's in the vocab.
단어 선택에 포함돼 있죠
Um, another thing to notice is that, uh, as with GPT tokenizer, uh, the fact that something is
또 하나 주목할 점은 GPT 토큰라이저와 마찬가지로 단어 시작을 의미하는
the beginning of a word, this space before the word is part of the token.
겁니다 단어 앞의 이 공백은 토큰의 일부죠
So and so am as the beginning of the word, and then the letters Am is a different token to just am,
그래서 AM은 단어의 시작으로 쓰이고 알파벳 AM은 문자 조각인 AM을 나타내는 다른 토큰이에요
the fragment of characters that could be within something more complicated.
더 복잡한 무언가에 속해 있을 수 있죠
You'll also notice that something like Tokenizers got broken into two tokens, one for the word token
토큰라이저 같은 것이 토큰 두 개로 나뉘는 것도 보이실 겁니다 하나는 워드 토큰이고
and the other for ISAs.
다른 하나는 ISA죠
So that's an interesting, uh, you know, a word ending Isa ISAs.
ISA로 끝나는 단어가 참 흥미롭네요
You could imagine that might be stuck on the end of lots of different things, and that's part of its
여러 가지 끝에 걸렸을 수도 있어요 그것도 토큰화의
tokenization.
일부죠
One other thing to notice is that it is case sensitive.
또 하나 주목할 점은 대소문자를 구별한다는 거죠
So so you can see that, uh, token with a capital T has been been taken there.
보시다시피 대문자 T로 시작하는 토큰이 저기로 옮겨졌어요
Uh, so, uh, the final thing I want to mention here is the tokenizer dot vocab.
마지막으로 말씀드리고 싶은 건 토큰라이저라는 단어예요
If you run tokenizer dot vocab, you get the, uh, it gives you the.
토큰라이저 닷 단어집을 실행하면 get이 나와요
It's the dictionary of the complete mapping between fragments of Words and numbers.
단어와 숫자 조각 사이를 오가는 완전한 지도 사전이죠
And you can see there's some pretty obscure things here.
잘 안 알려진 것들이 있어요
There's an awful lot of tokens that are available, and there's some quite odd tokens in here that are
사용할 수 있는 토큰이 정말 많아요 여기엔 꽤 이상한 토큰들도 있어요 다른 언어의
from different languages or used for different purposes.
토큰이거나 다른 목적으로 사용되고 있죠
So very much it does go beyond three letters, four letters, and you'll see a number of different things.
서너 글자 정도가 아니라 다양한 걸 볼 수 있어요
A um, it's printed out quite a lot of them.
꽤 많이 인쇄했어요
Uh, something else that I'll show you from this, uh, as I scroll back through all of our dictionary.
여기서 보여드릴 게 또 있어요 우리 사전을 쭉 넘기면서 보여드리죠
Get back here.
Get it, Get it, Get it, Get it, get, it, it, it! 이리 와요
Uh, is, uh, that you can also print, uh, comment that, comment this out.
주석 인쇄도 할 수 있다는 거예요
Uh, just what's called the added vocab, which are the special tokens that I mentioned.
어, 추가된 단어라고 하는 건데, 제가 아까 말했던 특별한 토큰이에요
Um, there's a bunch of these reserved special tokens, and sorry, at the top you can see here are
예약된 특별한 토큰이 여러 개 있는데요 죄송합니다, 맨
the special tokens that have been reserved in the vocab, uh, to be used to signal to things to the
위에 보이는 건 보캡에서 예약된 특별한 토큰으로 LM에 신호를 보내기 위해 사용되죠
LM.
글의 시작이죠
End of text.
그게 다예요
Some reserved, um.
예약된 것도 있고요
And then a start header, ID and header.
그리고 시작 헤더, ID와 헤더를 두죠
And then some other things here.
다른 것도 있어요
And a Python tag.
파이썬 태그도요
Uh, something obviously special there.
뭔가 특별한 게 있어요
So for whatever reason, these are the special tokens that have been identified, uh, as, as it being,
어떤 이유에서든지 이 토큰들은 특별한 토큰들입니다. 이 특별한 토큰들을 단어 선택에 포함시키면
uh, useful to include those special tokens in the vocab and provide them during training so that when
유용하게 쓰일 것입니다. 그리고 훈련 중에 제공해서 추론을 할 때나, 모델을 실행할
you're doing inference, when you're running the model, uh, to, to generate text, you can use these
때 텍스트를 생성할 때, 이 토큰들을 이용해서 모델에 무언가를
tokens to indicate things to the model.
표시할 수 있어요.
All right.
좋아요
Well, that's a bit of playing around with the llama three model.
라마 3 모델은 좀 비트가 있었죠
Uh, llama 3.1 tokenizer.
라마 3요 토큰라이저 1개요
When we come back, we're going to look at the, uh, the way that that this applies to chats in particular.
잠시 후에는 이 기능이 채팅방에 어떻게 적용되는지 살펴볼 거예요
And then we're going to play with some other tokenizers.
그런 다음 다른 토큰라이저로 놀 거예요
So see you then.
그럼 그때 봐요